NARRATOR: Egypt, the
richest source of archaeological treasures on the planet.
SALIMA: Ahhh, this is fabulous.
NARRATOR: Beneath this desert landscape
lie the secrets of this ancient civilization.
JOHN: Can you see why the Pharaoh chose this place?
NARRATOR: Now, in this series of excavations
Our cameras were given unprecedented access to
follow the teams
of archaeology at the forefront.
MAN: I drive so fast for the thrill!
WOMAN: It's an entrance, we can see an entrance!
NARRATOR: Revealing buried secrets.
MAN: They just told me they found something.
Ah. Look at this!
JOHN: (laughs) A sphinx!
NARRATOR: And doing
discoveries that could rewrite
ancient history.
-Aufff. -Ahhh.
NARRATOR: This time they are
new secrets of the boy king, Tutankhamun.
Aliaa uses innovative technology to reveal
surprising evidence about his grave
and why it remained hidden for 3,000 years.
ALIAA: Many thefts occurred, how come it was never found?
NARRATOR: The team of
Eissa discovered a lost hiding place
of the treasures of King Tutankhamun.
ALIAA: It's the most exciting discovery of my career.
NARRATOR: And Alexander discovered extraordinary things
funerary treasures
in a 4,000-year-old tomb.
Congratulations!
NARRATOR: The Valley of the Kings.
3,500 years ago, the great pharaoh stopped building
pyramids as tombs.
And these isolated cliffs were chosen for
become their graveyard.
Now, archaeologists from all over the world come
to discover
the hidden mysteries in the city of the dead.
It's the first day in the valley
For Cairo-born Egyptologist Aliaa Ismail,
and his team.
ALIAA: There's real excitement in this place.
People come from all over the world
They come to this valley. It's incredible.
I am very proud to have these roots.
It is one of the most famous necropolises in the world and I believe
What's special is that it comes out of nowhere.
NARRATOR: More than 480 kilometers south of Cairo,
in the heart of Egypt,
There are the limestone cliffs of the valley of
the kings.
After 200 years of
excavation, archaeologists have found 65 tombs
hidden among the rocks.
But only one has been found yet with its
treasure inside.
The one that belonged to the pharaoh, Tutankhamun.
ALIAA: Here is number 62, Tutankhamun.
One of those great discoveries of the century.
NARRATOR: British explorer Howard Carter
discovered the tomb of Tutankhamun in 1922.
One of their teams saw
some steps that continued below the sand.
These led to the entrance of the tomb,
buried under meters of ruins and debris.
What Carter found in the
interior inspired future generations of archaeologists.
Deep in the mountains, in the middle of
a labyrinth
of tunnels that passed through the rocks,
Carter arrived at the grave of
Tutankhamun, hidden right in the center of the valley.
Inside, he found
treasures that had never been seen before.
More than 5,000 priceless pieces including
golden statues.
In the mortuary chamber, the
mummy of the pharaoh wearing a golden funerary mask
was placed inside a
coffin made of over 90 kilograms of solid gold.
This intact tomb made Tutankhamun
in the most famous of the pharaohs.
Now Aliaa is investigating the life of this golden pharaoh
-Guaoooo.
NARRATOR: And why his grave remained
hidden for so long.
Aliaa's team was scanning and documenting
the grave for the last 10 years.
And they made an extraordinary discovery.
ALIAA: The idea here is to understand what happens when you observe
the images without color.
NARRATOR: The scanners
they remove the paint from the walls
to reveal unusual markings.
ALIAA: This was the scene
main, and here is the 3d of the north wall.
So as you can see here, it's the silhouette
from an image
and it could have been done while they were painting.
NARRATOR: The images
show the jagged outline of the face
that is hidden underneath.
That is caused by the tip of the brush
when painting when the plaster is still wet.
ALIAA: That's why the brushes made
a very light impression
and with this we understand that it was done in haste.
NARRATOR: But why did the builders
would they rush into such an important job?
The pictures on the wall reveal another set of clues.
Despite becoming the most famous pharaoh
from ancient Egypt,
Tutankhamun did not have a long reign.
He was just a 9 year old boy
when he became king and trusted his advisors
close to help him rule his vast empire.
As Tutankhamun
growing up, he was known for representing himself
himself as a warrior king,
going to battle in a chariot.
But the child king suffered from multiple illnesses,
including malaria.
He was only 19 years old when he died unexpectedly.
-Watch how it merges there...
NARRATOR: Aliaa thinks the marks that appeared
in the plaster
are evidence of a hasty burial
due to the sudden death of Tutankhamun.
ALIAA: The decorated part in the tomb is very small,
only the mortuary chamber.
The rest of the tomb is undecorated.
If they had had more time, all of this would be decorated.
NARRATOR: Although the
construction of the tomb may have been rushed
His treasures were all he had
that a pharaoh might wish to take with him to the afterlife.
So why this tomb?
It was hidden under a layer of stone for thousands of years.
of years when all the other graves in the
valley were looted?
To solve this
mystery, Aliaa will resort to new technology
as your research progresses
the whole valley.
482 kilometers away
north of Giza, in the shadow of the pyramids,
the greatest treasure in history will have
a new home:
a museum and center
billion-dollar research.
When the great Egyptian museum is finished, it will bring together all
the treasures of Tutankhamun
in one place for the first time in 100 years.
DR. TAWFIK: Having all the pieces of the tomb
of Tutankhamun together in one place,
It will be a fantastic opportunity to find
new facts,
new hidden things about Tutankhamun.
NARRATOR: After Carter removed the treasures
from Tut's tomb,
These ended up in museums outside Egypt.
Now, for the first time in the museum's laboratories,
scientists and Egyptologists
will use modern technology to analyze
each object.
DR. TAWFIK: Some details reappear and give us
new information
about these antiquities.
NARRATOR: But some of
Tut's greatest treasures are yet to come.
482 kilometers south, at the Luxor Museum, Eissa
Zidan is preparing
122 of these priceless pieces for the
transfer to Giza.
EISSA: Is everything ready for transportation?
I am very, very proud to work with this
type of pieces.
We have a great
responsibility in handling the Tutankhamun collection.
It is something unique in the
life to move this collection to Cairo.
NARRATOR: The packing list
of Eissa includes one of the famous chariots of Tut,
intricate ship models a unique head
of the cow goddess, Hathor,
elaborately covered in gold.
EISSA: In my opinion, this
cow's head, as well as the mask of Tutankhamun,
It is a very important piece in this collection.
-We're ready to go.
NARRATOR: After only four hours, the packaging
Eissa stopped.
One of his team
discovered something somewhat unexpected in the warehouse.
It was an old box that
Howard Carter used to pack and transport
Tutankhamun's treasures outside the tomb.
ALIAA: I've never discovered anything like this before.
It is the most exciting discovery of my career.
NARRATOR: The box had been missing, presumably
lost for decades.
and no one knew what treasures it might contain.
193 kilometers south of the valley of the
kings, near Aswan,
a Spanish research team from the university
from Jaén hopes to continue
Carter's footsteps and making new discoveries
that could rewrite history.
-Hmmm, here you go.
NARRATOR: Professor Alejandro Jiménez-Serrano
heads
the largest foreign team working in Egypt.
Today is the first day of the excavation season.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: Sorry for the mess.
We are sharing room three
team researchers.
This is my, my bed, it's supposed to be the best, sorry.
It's amazing to wake up and the first thing you see is
apart from the ugly faces of
your roommates, be it the Qubbet el-hawa, the hill.
NARRATOR: Qubbet el-hawa is one of the ancient necropolises
largest in Egypt.
So far, one hundred graves have been discovered here.
Belonging to the nobles
who ruled Egypt for hundreds of years
before the Pharaoh
was buried in the Valley of the Kings.
-Hi, how are you? -Hi.
NARRATOR: Alejandro's mission is to find more
unopened graves
and reveal more about these early Egyptians.
PROFESSOR JIMENEZ-SERRANO:
It's hard to explain how I feel.
It's not just nerves, it's excitement.
It's a mixture of feelings.
It is an honor
coming every year.
Now comes the hardest part of the day,
climb the hill.
NARRATOR: This is the tenth year of excavation.
of the team here.
WOMAN: It's very nice to be here again.
NARRATOR: There's a reason everyone is
excited to be back.
Last year, Alejandro
found the entrance to a sealed tomb,
but his permit expired
before he could explore its interior.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: Today it's 40 degrees,
and work in the sun, the day will be difficult.
NARRATOR: To protect against thieves
modern tombs,
They put up a steel security door to
block the entrance
from the vertical axis leading to the sealed burial chamber.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: Well,
It's been a year of waiting, a year of imagining the possibilities.
I'm very excited.
-Uffff.
NARRATOR: In Luxor, Eissa's team packed up
the treasures of Tutankhamun
to transfer them to the great Egyptian museum in Giza.
But in the warehouse, Eissa is ready to
open the lost box,
Carter's to find out what's inside.
The team meets to see if the box really contains
priceless treasures
from the tomb of Tutankhamun.
MAN: Ahhh. Fantastic. ALIAA: That's amazing.
NARRATOR: These delicate
pieces of wood are old parts of a ship.
EISSA: Thank you sir.
Mohammad atwa for this new discovery.
NARRATOR: Warehouse records suggest they might
be lost parts of
a model ship that Howard Carter found
in the tomb of Tutankhamun.
ALIAA: This is the head of one of the oars, like this.
And the remains of the gold
are still there after all these years.
NARRATOR: According to ancient Egyptian belief,
Ships played a key role after
of death.
That's why placing models of
boats in graves was a vital part of any burial.
The boats often came with the crew
because it was believed that
the replicas would come to life and
would help with fishing and transportation in the afterlife.
The pharaoh used a
special vessel for sailing through the sky
for all eternity.
Ordinary people too
I thought I could get to the afterlife by boat,
rowing down the Nile and towards the other world.
ALIAA: Here you can see the date of the newspaper.
Sunday, November 5, 1933.
EISSA: Howard Carter, maybe you read this newspaper before
use it as a base in this box.
NARRATOR: To identify the origin of these pieces,
Mohammad inspects
Carter's original inventory.
ALIAA: This is the photo
taken from the tomb and here we can find the ship.
It's lot number 321, it's the same mast that's here.
NARRATOR: The records
show that the box was sent to Luxor in 1973,
but it disappeared, presumed lost or stolen.
ALIAA: It's really exciting and new
discover one of the objects
most important of King Tutankhamun.
NARRATOR: Eissa believed the rest of the ship
was safe
in the Cairo laboratory.
and that they could finally rebuild it.
To transport the treasures
To Giza, Eissa's team must travel 643 kilometers
of deserted roads and busy city streets
before they reach the safety of the new museum.
Now two trucks will be needed to transport
the 122 pieces to Giza.
EISSA: This is a great moment for the collection.
It is the final voyage of Tutankhamun.
NARRATOR: But with such relics of
incalculable valor,
There is concern about a possible kidnapping.
EISSA: We are well escorted by police
and the army.
They will follow us for
the transfer from Luxor to Cairo.
NARRATOR: With security in place, it's time to go.
They will face a grueling journey of 12
hours through the desert
to reach Giza before nightfall.
Since Carter made the
discovery of priceless treasures
Tutankhamun's gilts,
Archaeologists have continued to try to
find out where and how
the ancient Egyptians
They found vast amounts of gold.
80 kilometers south of the Valley of the Kings, in the
edge of the eastern desert.
The gold expert, the Frenchman Thomas Faucher and the archaeologist
John Ward are on the hunt
of the origins of Tutankhamun's gold.
THOMAS: So, I'm going to. JOHN: What are you waiting for?
A traffic sign?
NARRATOR: The Eastern Desert covers more than
220,100 square kilometers of arid landscapes.
Inside some of the rocks are found
tiny grains of gold.
For 7 years Thomas has studied ancient techniques
gold mining.
Now he seeks to find evidence of this.
But this part of the desert is a very dangerous place.
THOMAS: You know, we have to go before it gets dark.
because it is not certain whether
We stay there because we can lose our way,
We can have an accident and it is also at dusk
when all the snakes are coming out.
JOHN: Snakes? THOMAS: Yes, vipers.
JOHN: Nobody told me there was one here.
THOMAS: There are horrible vipers, yes.
NARRATOR: The first stop, an ancient well,
could give clues about the location of the communities
mining
during the time of Tutankhamun.
THOMAS: This is the well right in front of us.
JOHN: It's dry. Look at this! It's very deep.
NARRATOR: Now the well may be dry,
but it was so important that the ancient Egyptians
They dug a well to honor him.
JOHN: It's beautiful, isn't it?
In fact, they applied
a plaster ceiling and then paint. Incredible.
NARRATOR: The text engraved on
These walls reveal clues about the gold miners
and where they were headed.
Ancient engineers built a network of
wells and rest stops
that stretched across the desert,
one day away from each other
allowing travelers and miners to cross
and safely explore the arid desert.
The carvings on the temple indicate that these wells
were driving towards the mines.
Thomas hopes to find evidence of people
manager
from the extraction of gold from Tutankhamun.
THOMAS: Now we must go further east.
NARRATOR: Like an old-fashioned treasure map,
They must follow the trail of the wells further into the desert.
In Aswan, in the ancient necropolis of Gubbet el-hawa,
Alexander is about to open a 4,000 tomb
years old.
Searching for the funerary treasure that could
contain.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: I don't know who is more
nervous, me or my team.
I want to go down now!
NARRATOR: After a year of
wait, Alexander can finally enter the tomb.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: It's amazing.
NARRATOR: Find a 4,000-year-old coffin.
The workers have inserted
a box covered with acid-free paper inside
of the coffin to prevent it from collapsing while
They examine the grave.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: Yes. We were very lucky.
It's impossible to explain what I'm feeling.
The burial consisted
in two coffins, the outer coffin and the inner coffin.
NARRATOR: Among the rubble of the outer coffin, Alejandro
see something extraordinary.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: It's full of wooden models,
but unfortunately,
the outer coffin fell on them.
NARRATOR: The chamber is filled with model ships,
similar to that of Tutankhamun's tomb.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: Find
This funerary ship in a tomb is rare today.
NARRATOR: But no
there is only one, there are four with their entire crew.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: You want to laugh, you want to
scream, you want to cry.
NARRATOR: This is the first time in 70 years that a group
of ships like this one are found.
The discovery gives Alexander a
extremely rare opportunity
to study such important funerary goods.
You must first safely extract them from the grave.
Alejandro calls his team of conservation specialists,
Sara and Theresa.
SARA: I have 1, 2, 3, 4 boats and their condition is very poor.
Yes, it is very difficult and the insects ate the supports.
NARRATOR: Termites attacked the wooden boats.
Sara sprayed a liquid adhesive to keep them together.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: So, we'll see if they are
capable of performing a miracle.
NARRATOR:
They prepare a crib
foam lined for transport to the boat
to the laboratory of
restoration but the wooden hull is glued
to the floor of the tomb.
It will require surgical precision and the use of
scalpels to free it.
Prof. Jimenez-Serrano: From the grave to the laboratory
It is perhaps about 40 meters.
But today there is a lot of wind, which is very, very aggressive.
NARRATOR: These ancient ships are extremely
fragile.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: Prepare.
NARRATOR: Now that the
The wind has stopped, the team sees the possibility of withdrawing
the first ship.
SARA: Carefully.
(background vocals) (music)
(laughs) Ahhh.
(music)
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: Perfect. That was exciting.
One of the best moments of my career.
SARA: We have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
8 people.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: We took many weeks
to clean and fix it
the pieces that, that, broke
a few centuries ago.
NARRATOR: As the team works on the ship,
Alejandro manages to open the
coffin to see who and what is inside.
After 2 hours of traveling in the middle of the desert,
Eissa discovers a problem with the convoy they are transporting
the valuable treasures of Tutankhamun
EISSA: I'm worried about the float.
NARRATOR: A thermal blanket that protects
Tut's golden chariot is coming loose.
If that happens, it could cause a crash.
EISSA: We'll stop to secure it.
NARRATOR: The unscheduled stop of this convoy
in the desert
carrying the world's most precious treasures,
makes it an attractive target for ladornes.
-You have to secure it well from above so that
the canvas does not come loose
Eissa and his team are unable to secure the thermal cover
that protects Tut's chariot.
EISSA: There are some problems.
NARRATOR: Upon removing the cover,
They risk the scorching heat of the desert
potentially damage the priceless treasure.
EISSA: Everything is fine.
NARRATOR: Now, Eissa needs to get the convoy moving.
HASSAN: We hope to arrive in Cairo safely.
NARRATOR: In the valley, Egyptologist Aliaa Ismail
has the mission to discover
how the tomb and the treasures
of Tutankhamun remained hidden for 3,000 years.
ALIAA: Robberies were common in ancient times
and in modern times
but it seems that this particular tomb was not
found.
How could it not be found?
NARRATOR: The ancients
Tutankhamun's tomb engineers had a plan.
Inside the mountain
They made a great effort to hide the grave.
The Pharaoh's burial chamber is located at 7.9
meters underground
and is defended from the inside out.
The engineers built
a wall to block the burial chamber.
They filled the hall
that carried the king with tons of debris,
before sealing a
final entrance and cover the tomb of Tutankhamun
with a large amount of rocks underground,
the standard protection of a grave.
But when Carter discovered this grave,
had more material on it than any other in the valley.
This may explain how it remained undiscovered.
for more than 3,000 years.
But how did those rocks and debris get there?
Aliaa joins German geologist Martin Ziegler
to investigate.
MARTIN: If you want to understand evolution
from the valley of the kings,
you must also understand the evolution of rock.
NARRATOR: Martin thinks there might be clues
on the rocks at the entrance to a nearby tomb.
MARTIN: Right at the entrance, a slab is hanging above,
a rock could fall from the cliff.
NARRATOR: Egypt is
hit by dozens of earthquakes each year.
So Martin set up a seismometer to measure
vibrations that cause rocks to fall.
MARTIN: With this one,
We estimate that it is about 600 to 700 kilometers away
from the Valley of the Kings.
ALIAA: What would happen if an earthquake occurred a lot?
closer to the valley
of the kings? How would it affect him?
MARTIN: A very strong earthquake
large could destabilize some portions of rock.
When you look at the history of recorded earthquakes,
time scales
historical, let's say thousands of years,
we have some
records of earthquakes of that magnitude.
NARRATOR: Could rock falls caused
by earthquakes
3,000 years ago explain the
additional tons covering the entrance
to the tomb of Tutankhamun?
MARTIN: In the geological and historical past of the place,
There could be falls or slips caused
by earthquakes that covered the graves.
NARRATOR: But there is no
cliffs directly above Tutankhamun's tomb,
so it would not be a direct rock fall.
How did all that extra material travel through the valley?
and completely covered the entrance to the tomb?
To solve this mystery Aliaa and Martin must climb
through the air
Deep in the eastern desert,
Thomas and John search for evidence of the miners
that produced
the gold for Tutankhamun's treasures.
They are trying to find a route of ancient wells
that gold miners
They continued on their journey to the mines.
JOHN: It's like looking for a needle in a haystack.
But I'm losing some kidneys. (laughs)
NARRATOR: 112 kilometers from the last ancient well,
Thomas and John head into the unknown.
With his GPS broken,
now they risk being lost completely.
JOHN: This piece of
technology is discredited!
It doesn't work. (laughs)
Look, it's literally on the right side.
and we go here and we have to turn around.
NARRATOR: But after two days of searching,
John thinks they've finally found something.
JOHN: What's that over there? At the base of
that mountain?
We found it!
THOMAS: Well, it seems
that we have found a very interesting place.
It is a settlement.
NARRATOR: It may look like stones and
scattered debris,
but to Thomas's expert eye,
the outline of old buildings can be seen.
THOMAS: We have the huts where people
lived and where he worked.
Yes, we definitely have the evidence here.
JOHN: Thomas.
THOMAS: Look, people have been working here
and we see, yes, there is even more out there.
NARRATOR: As they approach, John spots the
tools that the ancients
miners would have used to extract gold from the rocks.
THOMAS: Yes, that's the grindstone.
JOHN: It's a shredder. THOMAS: Yes, it's a
shredder. Yes, exactly.
JOHN: They'd break up with this. THOMAS: Yes, they would.
JOHN: Quartz. THOMAS: Yes.
NARRATOR: They are the remains
from an old gold mining camp.
JOHN: How many people are we talking about? 20, 30?
THOMAS: Yes, maybe there were families living here.
NARRATOR: Thomas has
studied ancient mining techniques for years.
But seeing this evidence firsthand
understands the suffering that the miners experienced.
THOMAS: You start with a piece of quartz like this and
you want to make something with it.
Therefore, you need
grind it and you have to imagine how much pain it takes
to break a single piece of quartz, doing that all
the day, in the ray of the sun,
hitting and hitting,
grinding and grinding and doing that for years.
NARRATOR: The evidence
draws a picture of the life of the desert miners.
They dug wells up to 10 meters deep.
in the stone
in search of precious ones
quartz stones containing gold.
Crushing quartz was a huge task.
mining experts
They calculated that to make a spoonful of gold
a team of
20 people working non-stop for a week.
THOMAS: It looks heavy. JOHN: Yes.
NARRATOR: Unfortunately, there is very little evidence left.
from these old mines,
but these settlements provide a new
perspective
of the communities and their difficulties in processing gold.
THOMAS: We have all the material that, surely,
were using,
with which they worked to extract and process gold
to send him to the Valley of the Kings.
JOHN: We found it THOMAS: We found it
NARRATOR: In Aswan, the team
Alexander was preparing to take out the coffin
from the grave they had opened.
The inscriptions
revealed that it belonged to a man named Shemai.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: They just hit the
lid of Shemai's coffin.
Rebecca, you are the first person looking at the
face of Shemai in 4,000 years.
(applause)
All right, everyone! Congratulations!
NARRATOR: The inner coffin
It is intact, but extremely fragile.
Alejandro's team reinforced it to protect
to the mummy inside.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: It is difficult to express the
feelings I have now.
It is a special moment because I have studied this family,
and it's almost my second family.
NARRATOR: Already in the
laboratory the beauty of ship models
begins to appear.
Termites ate away much of the wood,
but their excrement helped hold them together
parts of ships for thousands of years.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: We have some parts that remain
a very good state of preservation.
This head of the
man, it's covered with termite droppings,
but the wood is still visible.
NARRATOR: Alejandro has seen a different figure
to the other sizes.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: We can see in the center
from the boat a yellow face
belonging to a mummy, which would represent Shemai.
NARRATOR: This wonderful discovery will help the
archaeologists to understand
the evolution of funeral practices
in ancient Egypt.
PROF JIMENEZ-SERRANO: I always dreamed of discovering
something like that, and it's a dream come true.
NARRATOR: Alejandro's next task was
carry the mummy of Shemai
to the surface for the first time in 4,000 years.
In the Valley of the Kings,
Aliaa and Martin look for clues to explain
Why Tutankhamun's tomb was hidden
so long.
They have special permission from the government to use a
drone and so have
a unique perspective on Tutankhamun's tomb.
MARTIN: Here we go.
MAN: If we look towards
down we will be at the entrance of Tutankhamun
-right now. MARTIN: Yes.
We can see the cliffs behind us
and we can see the central position of the tomb.
And here we can see the rubble.
NARRATOR: Loose rocks and debris cover the
cliffs
behind Tut's tomb.
But the drone also reveals flooded canals,
carved into the rock by heavy rains
for thousands of years,
and that could be the missing clue.
MARTIN: We think that if we have a
flash flood,
that material can go down in these types of channels.
NARRATOR: Throughout history, the valley has been
hit by earthquakes
and occasional flash floods.
The waters would push the debris down the slope.
towards the graves.
The tomb of Tutankhamun is located on the site where
the channels converge
of water and accumulate tons of rock.
This, combined with
stone fragments from a tomb built above,
covered the entrance and kept it hidden for
more than 3,000 years.
ALIAA: It's very exciting for me, as an Egyptologist,
see Tutankhamun's tomb from here and see how it is
fits in the valley.
Its location is privileged and it was the most protected.
It was the most protected tomb of all.
NARRATOR: Tutankhamun was a boy king who served as
a minor role in the history of Egypt,
but because of his
tomb remained hidden for thousands of years,
his treasure was safe from thieves
and turned it into the legend we know today.
In Aswan, the team removed the mummy from the
ancient Egyptian Shemai,
to the surface for the first time in 4,000 years.
That was the culmination of 10 years of field work for
Alejandro and an opportunity
amazing to learn more about Shemai.
(background voices)
PROFESSOR JIMENEZ-SERRANO: 1.25.
1.25 is very small.
My daughter is more or less like that and she is eight years old.
I was hoping he was at least 20 or something.
It was a surprise.
I never expected that
It could be just a child.
On his coffin it was written that he was the person in charge of the
store management.
By controlling the store,
You control people because you decide who will receive
food and who doesn't.
NARRATOR: This new
Evidence reveals that Shemai held a powerful position
in Egyptian society at a very early age.
He may not have been a pharaoh, but like
the boy king Tutankhamun,
His status provided him with a grave and a safe pass
towards life after death.
Finally Eissa and his convoy of Tutankhamun's treasures
They arrive in the city after 12 hours.
EISSA: Ayyy, we're finally in Cairo.
greeted by heavy traffic.
It's very, very, very exciting.
We've been waiting for this moment. -Yes, of course.
NARRATOR: Tarek Tawfik, the museum director,
He is anxious to have everything safely inside.
TAREK: Hi Eissa, nice to meet you...
That's great, wait
Now that they are taking out these boxes
Tutankhamun's royal treasure began to emerge.
EISSA: You guys very carefully support the
don't let go of the platform
I can now say that I am very, very happy.
We accomplished the mission.
TAREK: It'll be like opening Christmas presents.
When we get these pieces out
and let's discover more details about how they complement each other
the entire story of King Tutankhamun.
NARRATOR: Finally Eissa can unpack
the priceless treasures.
Scientists and
Egyptologists can now study and analyze
each element in your new laboratory
high technology.
The priority is the newly discovered pieces of the ship.
ALIAA: We will review in
our database which of them would be related
with some boat in storage.
NARRATOR: For almost 100 years, the ship that was
buried next to Tutankhamun
to help you travel to
the other life had lost its mast.
HASSAN: This mast, yes. I think it fits right in there.
Here?
Exact!
ALIAA: It's very beautiful.
It's amazing that after all these years,
we still have new discoveries
and new secrets of this great golden king, Tutankhamun.
NARRATOR: 100 years after its discovery,
the impressive treasure
of Tutankhamun continues to surprise the world.
And the Valley of the Kings
shows why it is the best place in the world
to reveal the secrets of the famous pharaohs
from Egypt.